Guide to the Peruvian Collection, 1583-1892 RL.01017
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Peruvian collection, 1583-1892
  - Cordova y Urrutia, José Maria de. Restablecimiento de los archives destruídos pare former una exacta historia del Perú. (Box 11, Ms 27)
    Manuscript copy of articles published in El Comercio, Nos. 2796 and 2800 on Oct. 25 and 27, 1848, recommending the restoration of the Peruvian archives. This manuscript copy is exactly the same as the one in MS. 26, folios 61-66.
  - Odriozola, Manuel de (1804-1889). Colección de documentos históricos. Cuaderno 3. (Box 11, Ms 28)
    Lima, Perú. 1860. 93 folios. Index.
    This volume contains manuscript copies and newspaper clippings assembled by Odriozola chiefly of poems and essays published in the Peruvian newspapers El Telegrafo, El Pacificador del Perú, and El Mercurio Peruano after Perú became a republic in 1820. Most of the poems were written by the Peruvian satirical poet José Joaquín Larriva (1780-1832). The newspaper clippings include: a Memoria about the Chilean National Navy read at the University of Chile by Don Antonio Garcia Reyes on Oct. 11, 1846; a royal cédula of Sept. 15, 1802, granting royal priviledges to the city of Lima; a biography of General José de San Martin; a letter from San Martin to Bolivar granting him the direction of the war in Perú; and a Letrilla of the Peruvian poet and politician Felipe Pardo y Aliaga (1806-1868). Odriozola assembled this volume between July 27, 1855, and June 1, 1859. An index is included at the end of the volume.
  - García Moreno, Gabriel (1821-1875) Adiós a García Moreno. (Ms 29)
    Guayaquil, Ecuador. June 26, 1866. Printed broadside. 2 copies.
    Broadside printed at Guayaquil, Ecuador, in 1866 by the political enemies of President Gabriel García Moreno after he finished his first presidential term (1861-1865) charging him with tyranny and assassinations. During his second presidential term (1869-1875), his oppressive rule ended in his assassination by young liberals at Quito, Ecuador, on Aug. 6, 1875.
    Both copies transferred to the International Broadsides collection.
  - Callao, Perú. Estado jeneral de la matricula de los buques mercantes nacionales, su clasificación, estado y jiro. (Ms 30)
    Callao, Perú. July 16, 1853. Printed material.
    This printed broadside includes information about names, nationality, weight, owners, captains, guarantors, trade and conditions of the ships registered at the port of Callao on July 16, 1853. Signed by Alejandro Deustua and Juan de la Puente.
    Transferred to Rare Book Room.
  - El Aguila de Condorcunca. 13 de Febrero de 1847. Suplemento 2. Frustrado proyecto de monarquía en Colombia. Epitome de la memoria documentada que redactó en el año de 1833, el jeneral de Colombia José Domingo Espinar, antiguo secretario del Libertador Simón Bolivar. (Ms 31)
    Cuzco, Perú, Feb. 13, 1847. 2 pages
    Printed article about a failed project of monarchy in Colombia. Summary of a documented recollection written in 1833 by the Colombian General José Domingo Espinar, former secretary of Simón Bolivar.
  - Paz Soldán Benavides, Carlos (1844-1926). A mis conciudadanos. (Ms 32)
    Lima, Perú, 1892. Printed Broadside.
    An expression of Carlos Paz Soldán's views upon constitutional guarantees related to public meetings, the right of assembly and the right of reply.
    Transferred to the Rare Book Room.
  - Perú. Visita de Tesorerías. Ramos de Jerusalen y Cautivos. Balance del antiguo Ramo de Jerusalen y Cautivos, conforme á las liquidaciónes practicadas en el libro respective y últimos dates presentados en la Visita haste el 31 de Diciembre de 1869. (Ms 33)
    Lima, Perú. March 18, 1870. Broadside.
    This printed broadside is a balance sheet of the branch of Jerusalen y Cautivos of the Peruvian Treasury Department according to an inspection of the register book on Dec. 31, 1869. It includes the name of each account, any representive, the landed property, the annual revenues, the interest, and credit and debit balances.
    Transferred to the International Broadsides collection.
  - Travada, Ventura El suelo de Arequipa convertido en cielo. En el extreno del religioso monasterio de Santa Rosa de Santa María que fundó el illmo. S. D. D. Juán Bravo del Rivero del Consejo de Su Magestad dignisimo Obispo de Arequipa. Por el D. D. Ventura Travada. (Box 12, Ms 34)
    n. p., n. d. 26, 42, 36 [i. e. 416] pages.
    A copy of the original in the Biblioteca Nacional del Perú which was first published in 1752, and reprinted and published by Manuel de Odriozola in
    Documentos Literarios del Perú. Lima, 1863-77. T. X. (1877)
    pp. [5]-324. The volume is replete with details of the ecclesiastical history of the city of Arequipa.
  - Libro duplicado de Alcaldía donde consta la entrada y salida de efectos de Almasenaqe al cargo del Administrador del Puerto del Callao D. Manuel Lastra. Año de 1823. Razón de los efectos existentes en estos Almazenes del Estado de la Administración del Callao de años anteriores qe se comprenden en el presente año de 1823. (Box 12, Ms 35)
    Callao, Perú, 1814-1823. 81 pages.
    This manuscript is a duplicate register of goods and merchandise deposited in the warehouses of the Adminstration of the Port of Callao from 1814 to 1823. Information includes the dates of registration, description of the goods or merchandise, names of the owners, names of the ships, names of the piaces from where the goods were coming, numbers of invoices, and dates of delivery are specified. Names of British and American ships are listed arriving at Callao beginning in 1820. Like MS. No. 9 of this collection, this manuscript is an important source of information on commerce and shipping in Perú at the end of the Wars of Independence.
  - Libro Real del Ramo del Azogue de los Reales Almacenes de Santa Barbara de Lima al cargo del Guarda de ellos e inspección del Interventor que corre desde 1º de Enero haste el 31 de Diziembre de 1786. (Box 12, Ms 36)
    Lima, Perú, 1786. [26] pages.
    This original manuscript records the inspections of the warehouse by the interventor or comptroller Juan de Luque Marmol, to verify the amount of mercury and of dressed sheepskins used as containers for the mercury between Jan. 1st and Dec. 31st, 1786. Information about the dates of arrivals and departures from the warehouses, the weight, geographical sources, names of the owners or shippers of the mercury and the sheepskins are specified in the inspections done during that year. Francisco Argumaniz was the guard of the warehouses during that period. Pages are missing from the volume, but it contains all of the information specified in the index. This volume is a good source of information on mercury production in Perú, similar to MS. No. 3 of this collection.
  - Olmedo, José Joaquín de, 1780-1847. Versos dichos en Tacubaya en el convite que el Sr. Virrey Arzobispo dió al Sr. Diputado del Perú. El Dõr. Olmedo incitado p r. S.E.I. (Box 12, Ms 37)
    n. p., n. d. [1] folio. copy.
    This manuscript is a copy of a poem improvised by José Joaquín Olmedo at Tacubaya, Mexico, in 1811, on his way to the Cortes of Cadiz as a Diputado representing Guayaquil.
    For further information see:
    Poeslas completes de José Joaquín de Olmedo, Fondo de Cultura Economica, Mexico, 1947 (p. XI-XII, 56-57)
    where this poem was published.
  - Larrea y Loredo, José de (1780-1830). Observación sobre el caracter de los Indios, hecha por el Subdelegado de Pasco Dr. Dn. José de Larrea y Loredo. (Box 12, Ms 38)
    n. p., n. d. 1-3 [i. e. 11] pages.
    Larrea y Loredo, Peruvian diplomat and politician, divides into three periods the history of the Peruvian Indians and describes their values.
  - Luque, Angel. Memoria. (Box 12, Ms 39)
    Lima, ca. 1801-1806. [5] folios.
    Copy of the memorandum sent by Fr. Angel Luque to Viceroy Gabriel de Aviles attacking the canónigos and the Fiscal Ecltesiástico who had charged Fr. Iglesias, Parroco de Cathedral with disrespect to the Archbishop. Fr. Luque complained about the denial by the Fiscal Ecltesiástico of Fr. Iglesia's appeal.
    According to Manuel de Mendiburu's
    Diccionario Histórico Biográfico del Perú (Lima, 1931), Tomo I. p. 103
    , Fr. Angel Luque was declared an infamous author in 1812 for writing diatribes against the secretary and the treasurer of Viceroy José Fernando de Abascal.
  - Basadre, Vicente. Correspondence with José de Galvez and Fernando del Mazo. (Box 12, Ms 40)
    Mexico, 1785. [3] folios.
    Basadre's letter to Jose de Gálvez concerned trade with China, the discovery of mines in New Spain, and the importation of mercury from the Philippines through the port of Acapulco. Basadre proposed the establishment with Chinese merchants of an exchange of mercury for furs. Nutria and seal furs were available from the missions in California.
    This letter is followed by a note from Basadre to Fernando del Mazo and his reply of April 16, 1785. These letters are copies.
    Ms. No. 41 is bound with this manuscript.
  - Philip II, King of Spain. Cédulas and letter concerning the revenue of factories owned by churches and hospitals in Perú and collection of the Quinta, the royal fifth. (Box 12, Ms 41)
    Madrid, 1583-1587. 6 folios.
    Bound with MS. No. 40
  - Consulta a la Junta Suprema Central sobre la convocatoria a Cortes y número de representantes de la nobleza, y el clero que hen de participar en ellas. (Box 12, Ms 41A)
    n. p., ca. 1810. [9] pages.
    A consultation with the Junta Suprema Central concerning the convocation of the Cortes and the number of representatives from the nobility and the clergy that will be members of the Cortes. According to Antonio Cano Manuel's opinion the Cortes should determine its own makeup; the Consejo de Regencia agreed with his opinion. This body was the famous Cortes of Cadiz that wrote the Constitution of 1812. The Junta Suprema Central and the Consejo de Regencia were the supreme authorities in Spain during the enforced absence of King Ferdinand VII.
    Originally bound with MS. Nos. 40 and 41.
  - Arequipa. Prefectura. Correspondencia Correspondence and a proclamation concerning the Battle of Ingavi in Boliva. (Box 12, Ms 42)
    Arequipa, Perú, 1841. [2] folios.
    Copies of letters dated Nov. 19 and 23, 1841, addressed to the Ministry of State of Perú and to the Prefecto of the Departamento of Arequipa, Perú, signed by Fermin Canseco and Miguel San Román, followed by a letter and a proclamation to the citizens of Arequipa, all of which are related to the Battle of Ingavi that took place south of La Paz, Bolivia, on Nov. 18, 1841, and in which Bolivians under José Ballivián defeated Peruvians under Agustin Gamarra who was killed.
  - El Mercurio Peruano. Manuscript copy of a manuscript of the Colección de Papeles Varios in the Biblioteca y Archivo Nacional, Lima, Perú, concerning the foundation and publication of the first issues of El Mercurio Peruano, and also with the Sociedad Aciadémica de Amantes del País. (Box 12, Ms 43)
    n. p., ca. 1791-1794. [4] folios.
    According to a notice included with this anonymous manuscript, it belonged to Diego de Cisneros, a monk from El Escorial known as Padre Geronimo. The manuscript is highly critical of the founders of the newspaper and the members of the academic society, but it still is an important source of information in relation to both, including the names of the first academic and foreign members of the society. For additional information about the newspaper and the society, see: Alberto Tauro,
    Diccionario Enciclopédico del Perú, Ilustrado (Lima, 1966-67), Vol. III, pp. 176-177.
  - Perú (Viceroyalty). Arancel que se hen de observer en la recaudación del Real Derecho de Alcabalas de las internaciónes y extraciónes menudas que se verifiquen en las Garitas del Resinto de esta ciudad desde el 1º de Enero de 1811... (Box 13, Ms 44-45)
    Cuzco, Perú, 1811, 1816. 234, 212 pages
    These two volumes are contemporary duplicates of registers sent by the Court of Audit ( Contaduría) to the Court of Accounts ( Tribunal de Cuentas). These registers record customs duties ( Alcabala) charged for goods entering and leaving Cuzco at the sentry boxes of San Sebastian and Yanamayo. MS. No. 44 is the register for San Sebastian from Dec. 19, 1810, through Dec. 28, 1811. MS. No. 45 is for Yanamayo, Jan. 1-Dec. 28, 1816. The duties were paid to the royal treasury at Lima. The registers record the rates, the names of the persons paying the duties, the types of goods, and the amounts paid.
  - Cuaderno histórico de la fundación, población y establecimiento de esta ciudad de San Francisco de Quito con sus antiguos anales; y una serie chronológica de los Ilustrisimos Señores Obispos que ha tenido esta ciudad... (Box 13, Ms 46)
    Quito, Ecuador, 1794. [42] pages.
    This manuscript is a historical summary of the founding, settling, and development of the city of Quito, Ecuador, prepared by Juan de Ascaray, a notary. It contains a chronological list of bishops of Quito and is based upon documents in the archives of the city in 1794, especially a manuscript work by Dr. Miguel Sánchez Solmirón, dean of the cathedral.
    Eleven maps of Quito that were formerly filed with this manuscript are now in the Rare Book Room.
  - La Condamine, Charles Marie de, 1701-1744. Extracto del Viage de Mr. de la Condamine de la Academia Ri de las Ciencias a su regreso de la medida del grade terrestre en Quito pr. el Río de las Amazonas en el Año de 1743. (Box 13, Ms 47)
    n. p., n. d. [19] pages.
    Brief account of the nearly two year's journey of Charles Marie de la Condamine from Quito, Ecuador, to Paris, France, by the way of the Maranón and Amazon rivers, containing data on latitude, longitude, velocity of river currents, width, and depth of streams, and observations on altitude. La Condamine had come to America with representatives of the French Academy of Sciences, and with Antonio de Ullóa and Jorge Juán, scientists representing the King of Spain, to measure a degree at the equator to determine the shape of the earth. This was the expedition which proved that the poles were not round and silenced the enemies of Newton. La Condamine left the southernmost point of his meridian measurement on May 11, 1743, and reached Paris, Feb. 23, 1745. The author of this summary is not indicated.
  - Lima y Sn. Martín. o apuntes pare la histora. de la 1a. epoca de la Patria en Lima. 1821-1822. (Box 13, Ms 48)
    Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, 1822. [17] pages.
    A letter dated at Rio de Janeiro, August 15, 1822, in which the author, signed Un Arequipeño (i. e. citizen of the city of Arequipa, Perú), Charged General San Martín and Bernardo Monteagudo with tyranny, robberies and assassinations.
    Bound with MS. No. 48A.
  - Bando publicado en ValparaISO en 1º de Nov. 1823. (Box 13, Ms 48A)
    Valparaiso, Chile, 1823. [2] pages
    Copy of the edict published at Valparaiso, Chile, the first of Nov., 1823, signed by José Ignacio Zenteno, political governor of the province of Valparaiso, ordering the Spaniards to register with the authorities of Valparaiso within three days. Punishment for non-compliance was prescribed.
    Bound with MS. No. 48.
  - Al Eximo Sr. Libertador de Colombia y el Perú de su apasionadisimo admirador Antonio Gonzalez. 1825 (Box 13, Ms 49)
    Bolivia, 1825. 8 folios.
    Summary of the itinerary between the Province of Santa Cruz in the Republic of Bolivia and the Province of San Pablo (Sao Paulo) in the Brazilian Empire, dedicated to Simón Bolivar by his admirer Antonio Gonzalez, in 1825.
    This itinerary describes the conditions of the roads, the distances between the cities and towns in leagues (a Spanish linear measure nearly four English miles), the agricultural crops and cattle, the climatological conditions during the different seasons, the rivers and lakes, etc., from the Province of Santa Cruz passing through the Province of Chiquitos in Bolivia entering the Brazilian Empire through the town of Mato Grosso, the town of Guayas (Goiaz) and others, finally reaching the cities of Sn. Pablo (Sao Paulo) and Rio de Janeiro. Information about the troops, the clergy, the Indians and the economic and social conditions of the territories are included in the itinerary.
    This manuscript is a good source of information for researchers interested in Bolivian and Brazilian history, description, and travel, and social and economic conditions at the beginning of the 19th century.
  - Poesías del Colegio Máximo de San Pablo de la Compañía de Jesus. (Box 13, Ms 50)
    Lima, Peru, 1768. 22 folios.
    Latin poems of the Jesuit Major College of St. Paul in Lima on the occasion of the death of Elizabeth Farnese, Queen of Spain, wife of Philip V and mother of Charles III of Spain. The majority of the poems are elegies written in Latin expressing sorrow for the death of the Queen. Some are translated into Spanish. Laudatory poems on such occasions were typical.
  - Expediente sobre las expediciones de 1814 y 1815 por Andamarca al reconocimiento de las Montañas Peruanas. (Box 13, Ms 51)
    Santa Rosa de Ocopa, Perú, 1814-1815. 45 pages.
    This is a copy of a file on the exploratory expeditions to establish communications between Ocopa and Sarayacú by the Franciscan Fr. Paulo Alonso Carvallo, guardian and vicar of the Missionary College of Santa Rosa de Ocopa in Perú, together with Fr. Diego Ruiz and others. The purpose was to restore the missions of Ucayali in the region of the confluence of the Pangoa and the Chanchamayo rivers via the towns of Comas and Andamarca.
    The manuscript was copied out in 1847 by Fr. Julián Bovo de Revello. It consists of letters from Carvallo to the Intendent Governor, minutes of the town council of Andamarca, a diary of the 1814 (July 2 to Sept. 28) expedition of Fr. Carvallo, and information on the Fr. Diego Ruiz's 1815 expedition. Certain paragraphs of this manuscript describing the mountains and giving the distances between villages are quoted in Bernardino Izaguirre Ispizua,
    Historia de las Misiones Franciscanas (Lima, 1922-29), Vol. 9, pp. 13-18.
  - Poesías Sagradas de diversos autores. (Box 13, Ms 52)
    Lima, Perú, 1837. 25 folios.
    Included in this small booklet are several poems and Spanish tranlations of well known religious hymns. The translations are signed by F. Diego Gonzales. The authors are not identified in the volume.
  - Real Cédula de 24 de Diciembre del año pasado de 1788. (Box 13, Ms 53)
    Madrid, 1788. [3] folios.
    Royal Cédula given at Madrid on December 24, 1788, by King Charles IV commanding the Viceroy of Perú, Teodoro De Croix, to announce to the citizens of Perú the death of King Charles III and the accession to the Spanish throne of King Charles IV on December 14, 1788. This Royal Cédula was published at Lima, Perú on May 13, 1789, by order of Viceroy De Croix.
  - Candamo, Pedro. Carta anónima dirigida a Pedro Candamo. (Box 13, Ms 54)
    Lima, Perú. April 17, 1860. 2 pages.
    Letter from an unidentified person to Pedro Candamo discussing the planned delivery of a thousand ounces of gold, giving detailed instructions and threatening Candamo with death if the task is not performed.
  - Jesuits. Letters from missions (South America). (Box 13, Ms 55)
    Lima, Perú. 1587. [11] folios.
    Copies of 4 letters addressed to Fr. Juan de Atienza (1542-1592), Provincial of the Society of Jesús in Perú, from the Jesuit missionary Fr. Diego de Samaniego (1542-1627) at the Santa Cruz de la Sierra mission (now in Bolivia). The letters are dated April 10, June 1st, June 25 and August 3, 1587.
    Copies of 3 letters addressed also to Provincial Fr. Atienza by the Jesuit missionary Fr. Francisco de Angulo from the Tucumán Mission (now in Argentina), dated March 29, May 9 and June 23, 1587.
    Another 2 copies of letters to Fr. Atienza from the Jesuit missionary Alonso de Barzana (1528-1598) dated at the Tucumán Mission May 8 and August 20, 1587.
    Fr. Atienza was the founder of the Tucumán Santa Cruz de la Sierra and Quito (now in Ecuador) missions, and Fr. Barzana, because of his exemplary life as a missionary was known as the Apostle of Tucumán and Paraguay. For additional information about these Jesuit missionaries see: Evaristo San Cristobal, Apéndice al Diccionario Histórico-Biográfico del Perú (Lima, 1935), T. I., pp. 163-166, 285, 342-343, and see also: Historia General de la Compañía de Jesús en la Provincia del Perú (Madrid, 1944), T. I., Vol. 1, pp. 25-29.
  - Esquadrón de la Guardia de Honor del Excelentísimo Señor Virrey. 1 de Agosto de 1817. (Box 13, Ms 56)
    Lima, August 1, 1817. 1 folio.
    A report on the Viceroy's Honor Guard, giving the number of men, horses, etc. during July and August, 1817. Joaquín de la Pezuela, y Sanchez was Viceroy of Perú from 1816 to 1821. The report is signed by Ignacio Landaruri and José Rodriguez.
  - Perú (Viceroyalty). Caja Real de Lima. Razón de las Entradas diaries así por lo que producer los Ramos de Administración come los pertenecientes a la Contaduría, 1766-1767. (Box 13, Ms 57)
    Lima, Perú, 1766-1767. 96 folios.
    This register is a daily record of the sums paid by merchants, landowners, etc. to the Royal Treasury ( Caja Real) in Lima, capital of the Viceroyalty of Perú, between January, 1766, and August, 1767. The register records the names of the persons paying the duties, the types of goods, and the amounts paid. The majority of the revenues derived from two principal sources: the Alcabala, an excise tax on sales and exchanges of goods, and the Almojari-fazgo, an import and exchange duty. These taxes were collected by two offices of the Treasury, the court of Audit ( Contaduría) and the Administration ( Administración).
  - Woodcuts of a Bird and of a Genealogical Tree. (Box 13, Ms 58)
    Arequipa, 1834. [4] folios.
    The woodcut of the bird was made from a piece of wood found in an excavation at Cuzco. President Luis José Obregoso gave the order of printing a copy of the figure carved in wood. It was done at the government printing press managed by Benavides at Arequipa on Sept. 22, 1834. President Obregoso gave the copy as a present to Juan Gualberto Valdivia, a Peruvian priest and historian.
    The woodcut of a genealogical tree of an unknown family, also found carved in a piece of wood, was given to Valdivia by Obregoso.